A Guide to the Petersburg (Va.) Records, circa 1785-1959, undated
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Petersburg (Va.) Records, circa 1785-1959, undated
The Library of Virginia
1046884-1182150
23 boxes--15 found at State Records Center--Archives Annex, Library of Virginia and 8 found at Library of Virginia.
Petersburg (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions. Some records are copies/photocopies.
Acquisition Information
These boxes came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of records from Petersburg under accession numbers 27327, 32648, 33221, 37619, 37622 and 43614.
Historical Information
Petersburg, suggested in 1733 by William Byrd, honors Peter Jones, Byrd's companion on expeditions into Virginia's backcountry. Petersburg was formed from parts of Dinwiddie, Prince George and Chesterfield counties. Petersburg was established in 1748 and incorporated as a town in 1784. The towns of Blandford, Pocohontas, and Ravenscroft were added to Petersburg. It was incorporated as a city in 1850. Petersburg was enlarged by annexations from both Dinwiddie and Prince George counties, in 1921 and 1971. The city annexed land from Dinwiddie County in 1932 and land from Prince George county in 1945 and 1956. The city made a further boundary adjustment with Prince George county in 1991.
Scope and Content
Petersburg (Va.) Records, circa 1785-1959, undated, consist of the following series: City Administrative Records (subfield series include City Council Records, Sheriffs' and Sergeant's Records, Commissioner of the Revenue Records, Overseers of the Poor Records, and Treasurers' Records), Tax and Fiscal Records, Court Records(subfield series include Criminal Records, Judgments, Clerks' Records, Chancery Records, Personal Documentation and Court Finance), Justice of the Peace Records, Fiduciary Records, School Records, Election Records, Land Records, Wills, Miscellaneous Records, Bond/Commissions/Oaths, Business Records, Military and Pension Records, Marriage Records, Organization Records and Road and Bridge Records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Petersburg Records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm" found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Petersburg (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Public records--Virginia--Petersburg.
Geographical Names:
Petersburg (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Petersburg.
Contents List
- Records, circa 1785-1865
  City Council Records: Assessments of Lots (photocopy), 1785 (Accession 33221); Tax and Fiscal Records: License Tax Assessment Lists, circa 1830-1865; Court Records: Hustings Court: Criminal Records: Commonwealth Causes, 1797-1802 (Accession 32648); Judgments: Subpoenas, 1835.
- Records, 1821-1897
  Justice of the Peace Records: Magistrates' Executions, 1821, 1890-91; Court Records: Judgments: Executions, 1837-1848; Judgments and Dismissions, 1856 and Criminal Records: Commonwealth Causes, 1848-1897; Fiduciary Records: Fiduciary Bonds and Tax and Fiscal Records: Liquor License Bonds, 1841-1891.
- Records, circa 1800-1882
  Court Records: Judgments, Executions, Criminal Records, Subpoenas, circa 1800-1870; Tax and Fiscal Records: Receipts, circa 1840s, Tobacco Bonds, 1815-1818, Tax Coupon Reports, 1879-1882; Fiduciary Records: Fiduciary Bonds.
- Records, circa 1790-1908
  Court Records: Judgments and Criminal Records, 1790-1870 (Chancery pulled); Judgments: Executions: 1841-1860; Clerk's Records: Papers of Clerk Robert Gilliam, circa 1890-1905; School Records: School Commissioners' Report, 1839; Fiduciary Records: Fiduciary Accounts, 1890; Election Records. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, 1816-1920
  Court Records: Judgments; Commonwealth Causes; Tax and Fiscal Records; Copies of Deeds and Wills, Fiduciary Records.
- Records, circa 1867-1957
  Tax and Fiscal Records: City Jail Meal Books, 1943-1946, Memorandum of Real Estate, 1876-1890, Delinquent Tax Returns, 1867-1870, License Returns, 1868-1870, and Tax warrants, 1957; Election Records: Voting Returns, 1910-1911; Miscellaneous Records: Time book, 1929. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1819-1909
  Court Records: Mullen (Attorney) Receipts, 1886-1909, Judgments, Criminal Records: Commonwealth Causes, circa 1819-1894; Election Records: Poll Records, 1878, 1892; School Records: School Commissioners' Reports, 1840-1861; Tax and Fiscal Records: Liquor Bonds, 1881-1882; Fiduciary Records: Administrator Bonds; Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Notary Public Bonds, 1864-1865; UNPROCESSED.
- Records, 1844-1930
  Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships: Banking Trust and Mortgage Co. Loan Correspondence (1915-30); Tax and Fiscal Records: Affidavits for Ardent Spirits (1916); Court Records: Judgments--2 seals (1844).
- Records, 1857-1904
  Fiduciary Records: Fiduciary Bonds and Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Officials' Bonds (1900-1904); Fiduciary Records: Fiduciary Accounts (1857-1898); Tax and Fiscal Records: Applications for Delinquent Lands,(1899).
- Records, 1870-1916
  Tax and Fiscal Records: Application for Delinquent Land Purchases, 1898-1900, Daily Account Sheets, 1915, 1916; Election Records: Election Returns, 1870-1893, Abstract of Votes and Expense Listing of Candidates, 1897, 1912; UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1839-1951
  Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships: Prescription Receipts--Hancock's Drug Store, 1920, Matthews Pharmacy Order Book, 1921, Union Bank and Trust Company, Report on Audit, 1928; Court Records: Judgments: Garnishee Summons, 1869-1892 and Chancery Records: Chancery Docket (fragment), 1839; Miscellaneous Records: Bank Wallet - A.L. Bishop, circa 1920's, Correspondence, Cancelled Checks, Re: Willard C. Kidd, circa 1920s, Papers Re: Petersburg Savings and American Trust Company most related to Fiduciary Matters, 1929-1951; Papers re: Planters and Mechanics Bank, 1870-1896; Unidentified Index, Photograph - Unidentified Soldier, 1898.
- Records, circa 1786-1959
  Fiduciary Records; Tax and Fiscal Records: Jail Receipts and Fee Reports (1955-1959) and Memoranda of Real Estate for Non-Payment of Taxes, 1897. UNPROCESSED
- Records, circa 1794-1889
  Court Records: Judgments and Criminal Records, 1820-1889; Marriage Records and Vital Statistics: Marriage Certificates/Returns, circa 1794-1833; City Administrativer Records: Sheriff's Records: Receipts Collected, 1814-1815; Fiduciary Records: Fiduciary Accounts, 1873; Tax and Fiscal Records: Reports of Liquor Sales, 1878-1879, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1800-1806
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Officials' Bonds (circa 1808-46); Fiduciary Records: Inventories, Appraisals, Estate Account Sales (1800-46); Military and Pension Records; Court Records: Judgments, 1800 (chancery pulled); Plat of property along Adams and Walnut Streets. UNPROCESSED.
- Records, circa 1819-1935
  Tax and Fiscal Records: Sales of Delinquent Land (1893); Court Records: Judgments, Criminal Records: Commonwealth Causes, circa 1819-1919; City Administrative Records: City Sergeant's Receipts for Fines, 1910; Court Records: Criminal Records: Commonwealth Causes (1851-53); Tax and Fiscal Records: Deed and Delinquent Land Stubs; Court Records: Personal Documentation, Naturalization Certificates, 1918, UNPROCESSED.
- Records, 1828-1864
  Court Records: Judgments: Appeal Bonds, 1828, 4 items, Writs of Execution (Fifas), 1857-1858, 31 items, Commissioners' Reports, 1858-1859, 1861, 1863, 1864, 20 items; Tax and Fiscal Records: List of Delinquent Land Taxes, 1863 and List of Delinquent Free Negroes, 1863. Accession 27327.
- Records, 1878-1948
  Land Records: Plat of Cedar Grove, 1878; Miscellaneous Records: Newspaper, Petersburg Daily Progress, June 2, 1899; Court Records: Hustings Court: Criminal Records: List of Prisoners in Jail, 1889; Personal Documentation: Naturalizations, 1918 - Accession 37622 and Plats for Judgments, 1820, 1889, 1948--Accession 37619.
- Records, 1824-1902
  Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Business Records/Corporations/Partnerships; City Administrative Records: Commissioner of Revenue Records; Court Records: Cause Reports, 1838-1859, Clerk's Records, Commissioner's Report, 1833-1834, Court Finance, 1868-1902, Court Finance: List of Fines Imposed and Paid, 1824-1858, 1889-1890, Criminal Records: Pardons, 1877, List of Prisoners in Jail, 1873-1874, Prisoners Released from Jail, 1890-1896.
- Records, 1806-1903
  Election Records: 1859-1903; Fiduciary Records: List of Persons Obtaining Probate Administrations, 1831-1834, 1847-1849; Land Records: Caveats, 1856, 1858, 1868, Deeds, 1836, 1838, 1841, 1866, Deeds of Trust 1845-1903, Ejectments, 1806-1903, Inquisitions on Escheated Lands 1856, Land Records of Virginia State Land Office, 1857, 1881, List of Deeds Recorded/Transfers, 1898-1903.
- Records, 1805-1903, undated
  Petersburg: Marriage Records and Vital Statistics, 1805-1903; Military and Pension Records 1807-1891, 1902, Militia Roll, undated; Miscellaneous Records: Liens, 1889 1894 1899 1900; City Administrative Records: Fire Marshal Records, 1886-1888, Overseers of the Poor Records, 1814-1855 and Treasurers' Records, 1812-1848, 1870, 1896; Organization Records; Road and Bridge Records 1813-1832; School Records 1819-1855.
- Records, 1797-1954
  Tax and Fiscal Records: Appeal of Department of Public Improvement's Tax Assessments, 1901, 1903, Delinquent Tax List, 1842-1859, 1888, List of Delinquent Land Sold including Receipts, 1899-1902, Insolvents, 1842-1855, Land Tax Book, 1797 1803, 1846-1896, Personal Property Books, 1797 1803 1820, Request for Reassessments/Tax Refunds, 1821-1903, Salaries of Mayor, Councilmen, 1928-1954; Schedules of Insolvent Debtors under Bankruptcy; Court Records: Court Finance: Juror Vouchers 1857-1860.
- Records, 1800-1901, undated
  City Administrative Records: Sheriffs' Records, 1853-1873, Tax Tickets 1882; Tax and Fiscal Records, 1800-1901, undated.
- Records, 1789-1896, undated
  Election Records: List of Eligible Voters for General Election (1854); Court Records: Clerks' Records: Clerks' Correspondence (1822, 1825, 1896); Tax and Fiscal Records: Character Reference for Isaac P. Evans (1823); City Administrative Records: Commissioner of Revenue Records: Commissioner's Returns and Summary of Taxable Property, (1820-1822); Fiduciary Records: Guardian Appointment for John and Jane Worsham, undated; Bonds/Commissions/Oaths: Lists of Appointees to Various City Government Positions like Overseer of Poor, Sheriff, Clerk, Fish Inspector, 1823-1825; Land Records: Plats of Lots of Estates of William Haxall and James Haxall with corrections to survey for indenture of Hugh Dooner, 1835; Court Records: Criminal Records and Judgments (Memoranda, Summons, Depositions, 1789-1826; Tax and Fiscal Records, Tobacco Bond (1822), Accession 43614.